Hi, welcome to my presentation, From
Prompts to Review Harnesses Scaling AI
Code Reviews Across 70+ Software Projects.
Who am I?
I'm Guido.
I'm an executive consultant at CGI.
I've been working in the industry
for 15 years or so, and have been
with CGI for a few of those Now, what
are we going to talk about today?
First of all, why did
we even do what we did?
Then what was our initial approach?
What problems we came across,
how we solved them, what the
results of that whole process
were, what did we learn along the
way, and what our next steps are.
But why AI reviews?
We had critical manual findings in
one project in the middle of last
year, and as a result, we needed to
review seventy plus more projects.
The issue was one of those manual
reviews took a person like two or three
days of work, and we simply didn't have
enough budget or people for those manual
reviews So we knew we had to turn to AI.
But why did we build our own tool?
First of all, compliance.
We simply couldn't use a
public API from Anthropic or
OpenAI for that client of ours.
Then we wanted better long-term
cost control, so if one of the model
providers simply decides to jack up the
prices, we can just switch the model
or the model provider or even both.
Then we wanted complete
model independence.
Complete meaning we technically
wanted to be able to switch
to any model at any time.
There are obviously quality
differences, and we can't just use
any model, but technically we could.
And then we wanted better control over
the review criteria because, as I said,
we had that specific critical finding,
and we needed to check a lot of projects
about this finding, so we needed to make
sure that the review process actually
looks for that specific finding So
we started with our initial approach
being a simple prompt-based approach.
We used OpenCode as an agent runner.
OpenCode because we had previous
experience with that and code reviews
are code anyway, so that might just work.
So we had one prompt, one detailed
task markdown, writing down exactly
what we wanted the agent to do in
the review, then multiple checklists.
A checklist in that sense being a
cross-project list of review criteria by
project type, topic, or technology stack,
and one report template so the agent knows
what the final report should look like.
And the results look good at first,
because everything that comes
out of an LLM looks good at first
Which brings us neatly to our first
set of problems and solutions.
So the prompt-based
approach had some problems.
The agents just wouldn't perform
consistent, complete reviews.
They forgot to read files,
they forgot checklist items.
They just didn't really
follow the report template.
And what we initially thought that
it might be the context window, that
it's just too much context at once.
So we introduced some sub-agents
or instructed open code to
specifically spawn sub-agents for
certain tasks, which did help, but
it just didn't solve the problem.
And one of the highlights I always bring
up is a review where the agent afterwards
said, "I had this 700-file project and
read 11 files, and now I give you the
whole report over the full project."
Which of course is completely useless
because even the most skilled human or
agent could not give you a full report
for a project by reading only 11 files
of it But those weren't all the issues.
We had a very interesting problem
when we switched from Claude Sonnet
4.5 to 4.6, where the agent suddenly
started actively ignoring large parts
of the repository even though the
instructions clearly said that it is
very important to review everything.
We simply had to face the truth
that trying to force it through
the prompt is simply not reliable,
and we really tried a lot there.
We, of course, also asked the agents
why they did that, so we asked
basically for rationalization, which
was not particularly useful, but it
was fun, and that's why I want to
share two of those quotes with you.
First of all, "I understood that
the task was to look at everything,
but decided that the review was good
enough after looking at half of it."
And then, "I consider looking at these
files irrelevant in the context of
the review, even though that clearly
violates the rules." Of course,
those are not the exact quotes.
They are paraphrased slightly because
the LMS produce rationalizations
that are, say, a lot more
wordy than those short quotes.
But either way, in the end, we
knew that with our prompt-based
approach, we were at an end.
We just couldn't continue further.
It was just not reliable
to go down that path.
But how do you work with someone
or something that seemingly doesn't
only know the concept of malicious
compliance, but has fully internalized it?
We thought we needed a deterministic
process and some enforcement.
First of all, we looked for something
where we could take our review steps
from the task markdown file into a
deterministic review process, and
for that, we found Strends Agents.
Strends Agents SDK is a really nice
way to work with agents, by the way.
Then we took the steps that were
programmatically solvable, something
like reading in the checklist items,
generating the final report from the
review templates, and stuff like that.
Next, we looked at the steps that the
LLMs should solve, and for those, we
gave the agents only the very specific
tools that they needed for that step.
For example, when they are checking if a
checklist is applicable for the project,
they don't have to have access to tools
for issue management and stuff like that.
And also for those steps, we had a
very focused prompt so the agents
know exactly what they should do.
Finally, each step has a validation stage,
and without a successful validation, the
process does not move to the next step.
Most of you are probably thinking right
now, "Wait a minute. That man in the
video, isn't he talking about a harness?"
And yes, I am talking about a harness.
But at the time where we had that
idea, at the end of last year,
that term really wasn't widespread.
The important thing, though,
is did it solve our problems?
And yes, it did, mostly.
By taking programmatic control
over checklists and files,
we reduced hallucinations and
forgetting of tasks dramatically.
We could enforce the completeness by
requiring the individual results to be
handed over to the programmatic process.
And since the report was now generated
programmatically, it did finally
adhere to the templates we set.
And if for some reason a result
was missing, we could just send
the agent back to the necessary
step and make it fix their mistake.
Now this process, of course,
needs some kind of working memory.
So behind the scenes, we went ahead
and carefully designed a memory file
storage, which, for one, serves obviously
as the raw data behind the report,
but also helps us achieve future goals
like resuming interrupted reviews, at
some point maybe incremental reviews,
and, as a bit of foreshadowing, later
processing of the report data Speaking
of the reports, we of course needed to
make the results accessible, and we hit a
roadblock there pretty much immediately.
While during the test runs, we gave
the reports to some people to evaluate
them, and they obviously read the
whole reports in the production stage.
Pretty much no one wanted to
read a large markdown report,
and they were really large.
So our first step there was to break
that off into multiple focused report
templates, which helped a bit, but the
LLM output is still very wordy, and so
no one really wanted to read that either.
It dawned on us that markdown and text
are inherently just too difficult to read.
So we slop-coded a visualization tool
and integrated it into our quality
dashboard, which worked perfectly fine.
The developers actually interacted
with the reports, clicked through
the files, through the issues,
through the checklist items.
They could filter them.
They were happy.
They really used that tool and gave
us absolutely positive feedback Riding
on this high, we thought, how could
we make the developers even happier?
And we created an MCP server
for interacting with the report
results right in the IDE.
And that MCP server worked perfectly
fine, but in the end, no one used it.
Okay, I used it, and it really
worked very well, but the developers
just didn't want to use it.
They wanted the report.
They wanted to read it, take the
information out of it that they needed
for their specific task, and then get
along with it and not chat to a, an
LLM to solve the problem for them.
Even with that minor setbacks,
we still have the results that
pretty much speak for themselves.
We started in that whole operation
with two to three days of manual effort
for one review, and we reduced that to
one to two hours plus twenty euros in
tokens, which is an amazing reduction.
Of course, we all know that
LLMs make funny and/or stupid
mistakes, and honestly, that
happens in our process, too.
But we still feel that we are at ninety
percent of the review quality a human
expert would provide in two to three days.
And those ten percent, developers
just ignore them and take the value
out of the remaining ninety percent.
Combined with the efficient result
interaction we built, we got almost
exclusively positive feedback.
And while it was true that when
I submitted that talk, we had
seventy-plus projects, I can happily
say that up until now, we have
created immense value for over four
hundred projects with that process.
But what's probably more important to
you is what did we learn along the way?
First of all, even good prompts are no
guarantee, especially the longer ones.
The longer a prompt is, the
less likely the agent actually
follows all of its instructions.
And even if they seemingly do,
LLMs tend to follow instructions
while missing the point.
For example, very early on in the process,
we had a requirement that in the memory
files at the end, every file in the
repository needs to be marked as reviewed.
Then the LLM at some point said those are
a lot of files, and I don't think there's
anything important in there, so I just
take a batch job and mark every file in
a specific category as reviewed without
actually reviewing the file," which
is, of course, fully missing the point.
Combining that with the strange
behavioral change from CloudSonnet
four point five to four point six means
that LLM outputs should be continuously
evaluated if you want to make sure that
your process quality stays the same
or at some point, maybe even improves.
We also think that a harness is essential.
But to be fair, nowadays, this
shouldn't really be news to anyone.
What is still more widespread is to
just throw everything at the LLM.
But if a script can do the job, a
script really should do the job.
Of course, you can write the script
with an LLM, but once the script is
written, it doesn't incur any more cost
for each run, and it can also be tested
deterministically, making it easier
to uphold a certain level of quality.
In the end, both LLMs and scripts are
tools which need to be used properly.
While not being a major learning,
it's probably interesting for you what
kind of model performance we observed.
With the Anthropic models, Haiku
was just not reliable with tool
usage and also has a way too small
context window, so in the end it was
basically unusable for that task.
Sonnet, on the other hand, was
the cost-benefit sweet spot.
Opus, while being slightly better than
Sonnet when looking at the results, was
way slower and ten times more expensive.
And those ten times aren't just a
figure of speech, it's actually ten
times more expensive in our testing.
As for local models, and I'm talking about
my M4 Max MacBook Pro here with thirty-six
gigabytes of unified memory, they do work
in principle, but they are very slow.
And not only that they are slow,
they also have a big quality
bottleneck, the context window size.
So at least with the 27B models I
can run in my machine, the quality
is significantly below Sonnet and
therefore sadly not usable right now.
But with the advancements in
that field and the much beefier
hardware we ordered, that may very
well change in the near future.
Speaking of that near future,
what are our next steps here?
We of course want to evaluate new models,
especially local ones, as they come out.
We also want to try to introduce tools
for deterministic structural analysis,
like Graphify, into the process to
further improve token and time efficiency.
Then, especially when we go into the
incremental reviews direction, we want
to introduce checklist and findings
management so people can properly work
with reviews over a long period of time.
Finally, we may look into creating
pull requests and fixes automatically.
However, currently this is
out of scope for the use cases
we built that process for.
And with that, I want to thank you for
your time and hope the insights from
this presentation were valuable to you.